<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vanitie &amp; downe-fall of superstitious Popish ceremonies, or, A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Durham by one Mr. Peter Smart, a præbend there, July 27. 1628 : containing not onely an historicall relation of all those severall Popish ceremonies and practises which Mr. Iohn Cosens hath lately brought into the said cathedrall church: but likewise a punctuall confutation of them; especially of erecting altars, and cringing to them, (a practise much in vse of late) and of praying towards the east.</title>
            <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22640.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2885</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29401382</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29401382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1858:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vanitie &amp; downe-fall of superstitious Popish ceremonies, or, A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Durham by one Mr. Peter Smart, a præbend there, July 27. 1628 : containing not onely an historicall relation of all those severall Popish ceremonies and practises which Mr. Iohn Cosens hath lately brought into the said cathedrall church: but likewise a punctuall confutation of them; especially of erecting altars, and cringing to them, (a practise much in vse of late) and of praying towards the east.</title>
                  <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the Heyres of Robert Charteris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edenborough in Scotland :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: *, A-E⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cosin, John, 1594-1672.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:1"/>
            <p>THE VANITIE &amp; DOWNE-FALL OF SVPERSTITIOVS POPISH CEREMONIES: <hi>OR,</hi> A SERMON PREACHED IN THE Cathedrall Church of Durham by one Mr. PETER SMART, a Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend there, <hi>July</hi> 27. 1628.</p>
            <p>CONTAYNING NOT ONELY AN Hiſtoricall relation of all thoſe ſeverall Popiſh Ceremonies and practiſes which Mr. IOHN COSENS hath lately brought into <hi>the ſaid Cathedrall Church:</hi> But likewiſe a punctuall confuration of them; eſpecially of erecting Altars, <hi>and cringing to them, (a practiſe</hi> much in vſe of late) and of praying towards the Eaſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 4. 3.</bibl> 
               <p>O yee ſonnes of men, how long will yee turne my glory into ſhame? how long will you loue Vanitie, and ſeeke after leaſing?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PHIL. 3. 18, 19.</bibl> 
               <p>For many walke, of whom I haue told you often, but now tell you weeping, that they are the enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt. Whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is theyr bellie, whoſe glory is there ſhame, who minde earthly things.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Edenborough</hi> in Scotland, 1628. By the Heyres of ROBERT CHARTERIS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:2"/>
            <head>A briefe, but true hiſtoricall Narration of ſome notorious Acts and Speeches of Mr. IOHN COSENS, and ſome other of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions contracted into ARTICLES.</head>
            <p>WEe doubt not, but the world hath heard, of Mr. IOHN COSENS his ſpeculatiue and theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall Popery, which hee hath audaciouſly broached in his <hi>Booke of Priuate Devotions, or the hoewrs of Prayer,</hi> which booke one Mr. BVRTON a zealous Miniſter, and Mr. PRINNE a priuate Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, haue largely anſwered; though wee heare they were but ill rewarded for their paines; both of them beeing troubled for theſe their Orthodox Books by your <hi>high Commiſſioners,</hi> who ſtraine it ſeemes at harmeleſſe gnats, yet ſwallow Camels. We haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought it our bounden dutie as to publiſh this worthy Sermon; ſo to informe the world in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, how this COSENS hath turned theſe his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh theories and ſpeculations into practiſe.</p>
            <p>Imprimis, <hi>The ſaid Mr.</hi> COSENS <hi>hath vttered</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>theſe trayterous ſpeeches, in an open and affirmatiue man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;</hi> That the Kings highneſſe, is no more ſupreame Head of the Church of England, then the boy that rubs his horſe heeles <hi>(a courſe compariſon for a loyall ſubject) and this as wee are oredibly informed hath beene proued againſt him by the oaths of two ſufficient witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, this</hi> COSENS <hi>in a Sermon of his vpon the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Parable of the Tares, vttered theſe Popiſh and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſpeeches.</hi> That the Reformers of our Church when they tooke away the Maſſe, they tooke away all Religion, and the whole ſeruice of God: they
<pb facs="tcp:27942:3"/> called it a Reformation, but it was indeed a Deforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Hee likewiſe ſaid</hi> to one that ſwore by the Maſſe, <hi>in a frowning manner;</hi> That hee wiſt not what hee ſaid, and that hee ſware by a better thing then he was a ware of: The Maſſe is a good thing, and a good word. <hi>The Author of this Sermon telling him vpon occaſion,</hi> the Maſſe is diſallowed: hee replyed roundly, will you deny that our ſeruice is a Maſſe? <hi>Theſe are his ſpeeches, now behold his actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, this</hi> COSENS <hi>hath ſet vp 50. glittering</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Angels round about the quire of Durham Church, in long ſcarlet gownes, with golden wings and guilded heads; together with three other Images ouer the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Throne, one of them beeing the Image of Chriſt, with a golden beard, a glorious blew cap with rayes like the ſunne beames; which betokens in the Popes ſchoole, ſome Deitie in the head which it couereth, if it might be knowne to be an extraordinarie Idol to be worſhipped, as this Image hath beene, by ſome Popiſh people which came to ſee it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, On Candlemas day laſt paſt: Mr.</hi> COSENS <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>in renuing that Popiſh Ceremonie of burning candles to the honour of our Lady, buſied himſelfe from two of the clocke in the afternoone till foure, in climbing long lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ſticke vp wax candles in the ſaid Cathedrall Church: The number of all the Candles burnt that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, was 220. beſides 16. Torches: 60, of thoſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning tapers and torches ſtanding vpon, and neare the high Altar (as he calls it) where no man came nigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly, hee hath brought in a new cuſtome of bowing</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>the body downe to the ground before the Altar, (on which hee hath ſet Candleſticks, Baſons, and Croſſes, Crucyfixes, and Tapers, which ſtand there for a dumbe ſhew:) hee hath taught and enjoyned all ſuch as come neere the Altar to cringe and bow vnto it: he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Choreſters to make low leggs vnto it, when
<pb facs="tcp:27942:3"/> they goe to light the Tapers that are on it in the winter nights; and in their returne from it, hee hath enjoyned them to make low leggs vnto it againe, going backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with their faces towards the Eaſt, till they are out of the incloſure where they ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly, hee enjoynes all them that come to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Church, to pray with their faces towards the Eaſt, ſcoulding and brawling with them, euen in time of Diuine Seruice, which refuſe to doe it, and bidding them either to pray towards the Eaſt or to be packing out of the Church: himſelf hath praying and reading his face alwayes turned towards the Eaſt: when he miniſters the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r: he ſtands at the Weſt ſide of the Altar, (as he termes and makes it) not at the North, as the Common prayer booke enjoynes him: that ſo his face may bee Eaſt and his backward parts to the peoples faces, who can neither heare, nor vnderſtand him: hee hath remoued the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ancient Deske and Pue: together with all the ſeates, and the Deanes Pue which ſtood on the Eaſt ſide of the Church, to the Weſt ſide, that ſo their faces might ſtand Eaſtward: hee ſends the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgorers about the Church, to remoue all thoſe, both ſtrangers and others, which ſit downe with their backes to the Eaſt. So de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted is hee to this Eaſterne Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seuenthly, he hath diuided the Morning Seruice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <hi>two parts, the 6. of clocke Seruice which was vſed to bee read onely, and not ſung: hee chaunts with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Shackbuts, and Cornets which yield an hydeous noyſe, and makes that Seruice which was ſcarce one quarter of an houre long before, one houre and an halfe at leaſt: and this hee calls Mattens. The ſecond Seruice at 10 of the clocke hee calls Maſſe, which conſiſts of Epiſtles, and Goſpels, the 10. Commandements, and the Nicene Creed, which are onely to be read on Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes and Holydayes, by the order in the Common Prayer Booke.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Eightly, hee enjoynes all the people to ſtand vp at the</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>Nicene Creed, (a Ceremonie which your Church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes not) which he commands to bee ſung with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Shackbuts, and Cornets, and all other inſtruments of Muſicke, which were vſed at the Conſecration of</hi> NAEVCHADONOZERS <hi>golden Image, (vnfit Inſtruments for Chriſtian Churches where men come for to pray, and not for to chaunt, or heare a ſound or conſort of they know not what) Each who refuſe to ſtand during this muſicall Cries (which laſts for halfe an houre)</hi> Mr. COSENS <hi>himſelfe hath gone and rayſed them vp, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Diuine Seruice, to the great diſturbance of all there preſent, bidding them to depart out of the Church, and nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vp their pue doores in deſpite of the Deane and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Praebends, that ſo they might not come into their ſeates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly, hee hath turned moſt of the Seruice into Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
               <hi>and ſinging, ſo that the people vnderſtand it not no more then they doe Greeke or Hebrew: He hath brought meere ballads and Jigs into the Church, and commanded them to bee ſung for Anthems: and among many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the three Kings of Colen,</hi> IASPER, MEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHIOR <hi>and</hi> BALTHASER. <hi>Hee will not ſuffer ſo much as the holy Communion to bee adminiſtred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an hideous noyſe of vocall and inſtrumentall Muſicke, (the tunes whereof are all taken out of the Maſſe-booke:) whereby the peoples mindes are wholly withdrawne from the holy duty which they are about, and from the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſts bitter death and paſſion. On the faſt day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eaſter laſt, he commanded the laſt prayer at the end of the Communion, to be ſung with the Organ as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them, ſo that no man could vnderſtand one word, in ſo much that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cople riſing vp and ſitting when it began to bee ſung,</hi> Mr. COSENS <hi>call'd to them that ſate neare about them, ſaying, you muſt kneele, you muſt kneele, it is a prayer: then all the congregation knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:27942:4"/> downe, and prayed very deuoutly they knew not what. It was tht fondeſt Faſt that euer any man ſaw, it being rather a Triumph, then any Faſt or Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly, he hath brought diuers old Copes which haue</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
               <hi>beene vſed in May-games heretofore, one of them hauing the picture of the Trinitie embroydered vpon it, and theſe Copes hee would enjoyne the Praebends conſtantly to weare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleuenthly, hee hath imployed diuers Recuſant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
               <hi>(and ſuch onely in making of wax candles, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes and glaſſe windowes; in guilding and painting of Images and the Altar, fit workemen for ſuch Idolatrous workes, and incite inſtruments to reuiue and ſet vp Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie once againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twelfely, hee hath violently inforced the obſeruation</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               <hi>of thoſe Ceremonies, going about the Church like a mad man, thruſting ſome out by the head and ſhoulders, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them Pagans, when they ſtood quietly hearing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and refuſing to obſerue his Popiſh Ceremonies. Hee hath likewiſe gone about the Altar (for ſo hee calls it) before the Communion, croſſing the cuſhions, kiſſing the Altar clothes, and ſmacking them with his lippes: in ſo much, as ſome ſeeing him ſo ridiculouſly occupied, ſayd one to another, looke, looke, is not the man mad, looke I pray is hee not mad. Theſe and ſundry other Popiſh Innouations hath Mr.</hi> COSENS <hi>brought into the Church of Durham: and now ſee their fruits. One Mr.</hi> FRANCIS BVRGONIE <hi>Parſon of Wermoth, following Mr.</hi> COSENS <hi>his practiſes, hath taken away the Communion table out of his Pariſh Church, and in ſtead thereof hath erected an Altar in the Eaſt end of the Chancell, made of a graue-ſtone. This ſtone he hath layd vpon a wall, not on a frame; he hath adorned it with guilded hangings round about it, contrary to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Booke: this Altar hee worſhippeth with the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:27942:5"/> of his knee vnto it, and there both hee and his Curate read part of the Seruice, ſo that moſt of the people on both ſides, can neyther heare, nor ſee them. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Mr.</hi> BVRGONIE <hi>many pariſh Churches elſe are reported to follow, to the great offence of Religious people, the great advancement of Popery and Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are like to overflow the whole Byſhoppricke of Durham if they are not in time ſuppreſſed: In ſo much that the Papiſts of Durham ſay openly:</hi> The Proteſtants need not labour to bring vs to them, for they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming apace to vs. <hi>Thus, thus alas,</hi> Grex totus in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris vnius ſcabie cadit: <hi>Our prayer, our deſire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this preſent aſſembly of Parliament, is but this:</hi> Pereat vnus, ne pereamus omnes. <hi>Let Mr.</hi> COSENS <hi>with all his great Abbetters and Diſciples, rather periſh with theyr pardons, (which wee heare his potent Byſhop patron, who ſhould haue rather procured them an helter then a pardon, had hee any ſparke of loue to your Religion in him, hath of late procured,) then that both you and wee, with both our States and Churches ſhould periſh by their Pardons, which can neuer expiate nor diſanull theſe great offences.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN THE CATHEDRALL CHVRCH OF <hi>DVRHAM.</hi> IVLY 7. 1628.</p>
            <p>BY PETER SMART.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 31. 6. v.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>I hate them that holde of ſuperſtitious vanities.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted, 1628:</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:27942:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27942:6"/>
            <head>Pſalme. 31. part of the 6. verſe.</head>
            <p>IN the common tranſlation, <hi>I haue hated them that hold of ſuperſtitious vanities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the new tranſlation, <hi>Them that regard lying vanities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Geneva</hi> tranſlation, <hi>Them that giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to deceitfull vanities:</hi> whereupon they giue this good note. This affection ought to be in all Gods children, to hate whatſoever thing is not graunted vpon Gods word, as deceitfull and vaine.</p>
            <p>Such are all humane Traditions, <hi>Ethelothreſkiai,</hi> ſuperſtitious will-worſhips the inventions of mans braine.</p>
            <p>The vulgar Latine hath <hi>Odisti, thou ô God hateſt.</hi> And <hi>Vatab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> hath, <hi>Odi obſervantes vanitates fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra,</hi> or <hi>vanitates mendacy, vaine vanities, or the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of alye.</hi> That is ſaith he;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Odi obſervantes opera quae prae ſe ferunt vanitatem et mendacium: id eſt eos qui ſuperſtitioni ſtudent, &amp; ea obſervant, quae à vero Dei cultu animos piorum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I hate them that obſerue workes carrying a ſhew of, or which vphold and countenance vanity and falſhood. That is hate the followers and favourers of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27942:7"/> obſerving things which withdraw godly mindes, from the true worſhip of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wow whereas ſome haue <hi>Odi,</hi> other <hi>Odiſti, God hateth,</hi> or <hi>I hate;</hi> they are all one, to one effect, for we muſt hate what God hateth, we muſt loue what God loveth; wee muſt apply our ſelues to Gods will, and conforme our ſelues to the ſimilitude of God, after whoſe image we are made, as much as we can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be you perfect,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>as your heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father is perfect.</hi> Therefore we muſt hate with a perfect hatred, whatſoever God hateth: as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal. 139. 21. ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doe not I hate them ô Lord that hate thee? Doe not I earneſtly contend with thoſe that riſe vp againſt thee? Yea I hate them with a perfect hatred, or vnfeined ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, I count them mine enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On which words one obſerveth well, The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet teacheth vs boldly to contemne all the hatred of the wicked, and friendſhip of the world, when they would hinder vs from ſerving God ſincerely.</p>
            <p>God is good, yea goodneſſe it ſelfe; Therefore it is not poſſible but God ſhould loue beſt that which is moſt like himſelfe, and hate the contrary: So muſt we doe, not loue our ſelues, or that which is like our ſelues, for we are nought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnis homo mendax, every man is a lyer, and the imaginations of mans heart are onely evill continually</hi> ſaith God.</p>
            <p>Therefore we muſt not loue but hate our owne imaginations, inventions, and lyes; and loue God who is good, and Chriſt who is truth, vnder
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27942:7"/> whoſe lipps, no vanity, no guile, no lye can lie.</p>
            <p>As a Father ſaith, expounding my text: <hi>Recte veritas odit vanitatem, quia vanitas in falſitate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſtit odiſſe enim dicitur id quod reprobat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt being truth, muſt needes hate vanity, becauſe vanity conſiſts in falſhood; for what a man hates, that he reiects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſau</hi> was a reprobate, reiected of God, becauſe God hated him: As we reade in the firſt of <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, Iacob haue I loved, but Eſau haue I hated;</hi> yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may not imitate God, in hating any man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence, that we thinke him a reprobate.</p>
            <p>We may not preſume to enter into Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and giue ſentence of election, or reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon any. Becauſe we know not, he that now ſtands, whether he may fall, and he that hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, whether he may riſe againe, and ſtand.</p>
            <p>Therefore in that reſpect we muſt hate none; we muſt loue our enemies and all.</p>
            <p>As our Saviour ſaith in the 5. of <hi>Matth. Yee haue heard that it hath beene ſaid of ould: Loue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thine enemy: but I ſay vnto you, Loue your enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, 1. Epiſt. 3. chap. <hi>He that loveth not his brother abideth in death.</hi> And againe, <hi>He that hateth his brother, walketh in darkneſſe.</hi> And yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>gaine, He that hateth his brother, is a manſlayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was <hi>David</hi> a manſlayer? did he walke in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and abide in death? becauſe he hated them that hold of ſuperſtitious vanities?</p>
            <p>No verily: for he hated not their perſons, but their iniquities, their evill workes, and affections,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27942:8"/> he did wiſh their amendment, and ſaluation, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God for an example, of whom thus he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, in his 5. Pſal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou art not a God that loveth wickedneſſe, thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt all them that worke vanity.</hi> Yet he ſaith elſe where: <hi>Thou ô Lord ſaveſt both man and beaſt, how excellent is thy mercy ô God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which appeareth, in that he maketh his Sunne to ſhine, and his raigne to fall vpon iuſt, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt. And as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>he would haue all to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore he loveth the man, though he hate their manners, their naughtineſſe, and vanities.</p>
            <p>So muſt we do, as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> bidds vs, in his 5. ch. 15. v. <hi>Hate the evill, and leue the good:</hi> we muſt not ſimply hate, nor ſimply loue, becauſe no man is ſo abſolutely evill, but he hath ſome good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; nor ſo abſolutely good, but he hath ſome bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: As our Saviour ſaith, <hi>There is none good but God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then? they that holde of ſuperſtitious va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, muſt we not hate them? Not their perſons, which may perhaps haue ſome ſparkes, ſome tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of goodneſſe; but their badneſſe is to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and themſelues, <hi>quatenus,</hi> ſo farre forth, as they invent, and maintaine ſuperſtitious vanities, oppoſite to Gods Law, which they ought to loue.</p>
            <p>As <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth, in his 119. Pſal. 113. verſ. <hi>I hate vaine inventions, but thy law doe I loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So muſt we, loue Gods law, which forbiddeth i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, and hate vaine inventions, and the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of vanities, when they would inſnare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle vs with their fraudulent impoſtures, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27942:8"/> and allure vs to their ſuperſtitious and idol ſervices.</p>
            <p>So farre forth we muſt hate them, though they be never ſo neere, and deare vnto vs: As our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our teacheth vs, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 26. verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man come to me, and hate not his father and mother, brother and ſiſter, wife and children, he can not be my Diſciple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, he that caſts not off all affections, and deſires, which draw him from God to the world, from Chriſt to Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>So then it is no impiety to hate our carnall and naturall friends, when they become our ghoſtly enemies, hindering Gods glory and our ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we hate them ſecretly, hold our tongues, and let them alone. As the Prophet <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ephraim is turned after Idols; Let him alone;</hi> that is, trouble not your ſelues with him, he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible, In a deſperate caſe; Let him alone, let him periſh in his ſins: But we muſt indeavour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our <hi>Ephraimites,</hi> hoping to reclaime them, from their Idols, after which of late they haue ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily turned.</p>
            <p>But if they proue ſtubborne, and ſtifnecked, then muſt we cry aloud, and proclaime their folly: we muſt diſcover their blindneſſe, and nakedneſſe to the world; we muſt perſecute them with fire and ſword; fire of zeale, and ſword of Gods word; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the lawes of God, and the King on our ſide.</p>
            <p>As it is ſaid in the 17. <hi>Apoc. 16. ver. The 10 Hornes, that is the 10. Nations ſhall hate the Whore of Babylon, the Church of Rome, and ſhall make her deſolate, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27942:9"/> and ſhall eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what are thoſe vaine ſuperſtitions, the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whereof ought to be hated? Some thinke Magicall arts are meant thereby; to which ſaith <hi>Pliny, Orientales populi ad inſaniam uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> addicti ſunt. The Eaſterne people ranne mad after Magick;</hi> which Gods Law vtterly condemnes.</p>
            <p>But the ſuperſtitious vanities in my text, are more generall: <hi>Vanitiy of vanities,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) all is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> beſide the feare of God and keeping of his commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe vanities,</hi> ſaith a learned interpreter, <hi>are hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane traditions, ſuperſtitious Ceremonies, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine and over throw both the Law and the Goſpell;</hi> after which Ceremonies, <hi>Orientales,</hi> our Eaſt-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers runne made in a manner.</p>
            <p>And what are Ceremonies? are all vaine? are all ſuperſtitious? God forbid.</p>
            <p>Many are tolerable, A few neceſſary;</p>
            <p>Moſt are ridiculous, And ſome abominable.</p>
            <p>Indeed in the beginning, when the law was firſt publiſhed, it pleaſed Almighty God to traine vp the people of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> vnder a multitude of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, to keepe them in exerciſe, and helpe their infirmity.</p>
            <p>By the externall obſervation of which, he would accuſtome them, to his ſpirituall worſhip; and nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture them, in his feare and obedience; till the comming of Chriſt, who was the end, the comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the conſummation of Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>For when Chriſt had appeared, who was the truth and ſubſtance, the Shadowes departed: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27942:9"/> would he burden his Church, with traditions and rudiments any longer.</p>
            <p>Onely to preſerue the memory of his benefits, he ordeined two Sacraments, &amp; left to his Church liberty to make Lawes and Canons, for order and comelineſſe agreeable to his word.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Ceremoniarum anima,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>eſt verbum Dei: The life, and ſoule of every Ceremony, is the word of God;</hi> without which, it is dead and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>But Popes, and papall Prelates, not content with that ſimplicity which pleaſed the Apoſtles, and primitiue Church; would needes adde Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to Ceremony, increaſing their number <hi>in infinitum,</hi> till they had heapt vp a world of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which they adorn'd with worldly ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and bravery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adeo vt, &amp; Gentes &amp; Iudeos, externi cultus ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitione Chriſtiani vicerint,</hi> ſaith <hi>Szegedine. Inſomuch as Chriſtians haue ſurpaſſed both Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles in the ſuperſtition of externall worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which malady, or plague rather of the Church, began then to prevaile,</hi> ſaith he; <hi>Quando relicto verbo Dei mundana ſapientia adminiſtrari caepit religio Chriſti; When the government of Chriſts religion began to be managed, nay mard, and mangled with worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; Gods word being abandoned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not one among a thouſand, can be content to ſerue God, in ſpirit and truth; but he will affect ſome ſuperſtitious Ceremony, to worſhip God therewith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas Chriſts Church, in ſtead of many rites, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27942:10"/> ſignes, of which the Iewiſh religion conſiſted: A Chriſto acceperit paucam,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>eadem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> factu facillima, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu auguſtiſsima, obſervatione caſtiſsima.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Church hath received of Chriſt but a few; and thoſe moſt eaſie to be done, maieſticall for contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, chaſt and vndefiled in obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid hac ad inſulſas Caeremoniarum nugas? Quid ad ſuperſtitionem pluſquam Iudaicam? Quid ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laricam tyrannidem quae extruciat miſeras conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias? Quid ad tot Idololatriae portenta?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are theſe to the trifles of vnſavoury Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies? To ſuperſtition more then Iudaicall? To their diveliſh tyranny in tormenting wretched conſciences? Nay what are they to the prodigious monſters of Popiſh Idolatry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon he concludeth: <hi>Non eſſe Caeremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multitudine onerandam Eccleſiam: Chriſts Church may not be over whelmed with an Ocen Sea of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt fly the ſuperfluous furniture of pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous rites, and Papall Pageants, deviſed onely to aſtoniſh ſimple people, to raviſh their eyes, and mindes, and to amaze them with admiration.</p>
            <p>Now indeed the originall cauſe of moſt of our ſuperſtitious ceremonies, is that Popiſh opinion; that Chriſts Church hath yet Prieſts, Sacrifices, and Altars.</p>
            <p>Whereas in truth Chriſt was ſent of God to be the laſt prieſt, which ſhould offer the laſt Sacrifice, vpon the laſt Altar, that ever the world ſhould haue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He had,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Hebr. 7. Aparabaton ieroſunen;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27942:10"/> a Prieſthood which could not paſſe or be reſigned to any ther: He was not to haue any ſucceſſour, being a Prieſt for ever after the order of</hi> Melchiſedick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having neither beginning of dayes, nor end of life, but made like vnto the Sonne of God abideth a Prieſt continually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not made as the ſonnes of</hi> Aaron <hi>were after the law of a carnall commandement; but after the power of an endleſſe life;</hi> ſaith he, in the 16. verſe. For they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mortall men could not otherwiſe continue but by their lineall ſucceeding of their dying fathers one after another till the paſſion of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>After whoſe ſacrifice offered on the Croſſe, which was the concluſion and conſummation of all ſacrifices: the whole Ceremoniall Law, Moſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Sacrifices, and Prieſthood, were to end, with the beautifull Temple, and Altar therein.</p>
            <p>Onely the ſacrifice of prayer, of praiſe, &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, which every faithfull man and woman muſt offer to God vpon the moſt holy Altar Chriſt, is left to the Church.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Ireneus</hi> calls him, <hi>lib. 4. Altare noſtrum Chriſtus Chriſt is our Altar.</hi> And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſtus eſt Victima, Sacerdos, Altare, Deus &amp; homo, omnia in omnibus pro nobis factus: Chriſt is the Sacrifice, the Prieſt, the Altar, both God and man, made all in all for our ſakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To revive therefore and raiſe vp againe Iewiſh types and figures long ſince dead and buried; in bringing in Altars in ſtead of Tables, Prieſts in ſtead of Miniſters; propitiatory ſacrifices in ſtead of Sacraments. Is it not Antichriſtian preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27942:11"/> and ſacrilegious impiety, robbing Chriſt of his honour, and vs of our ſalvation?</p>
            <p>What is it elſe but an apoſtacy? a publike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation to renounce the onely ſacrifice, and the onely ſacrificer Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is the reiteration,</hi> ſaith a learned writer, <hi>of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatory ſacrifice offered by Chriſt vpon the Altar of the Croſſe, and the ſurrogation of an vpſtart Prieſt, for Chriſt the eternall Sacrificer, and Prieſt for ever after the order of</hi> Melchiſedeke.</p>
            <p>The ordinary Gloſſe ſaith well. <hi>Externi ritus &amp; Ceremoniae Legis, quia fuerunt vmbra Chriſti tum venturi, et myſteriorum, ideo adveniente veritate E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelica, illicita facta ſunt, &amp; evannerunt: The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall rites and Ceremonies of the Law, becauſe they were ſhadowes of Christ to come, and of his myſteries, therefore the truth of the Goſpell being once come, they, are made vnlawfull, and haue vaniſhed out of ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ought not then to be patternes or preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents for Chriſtians to follow ſince the comming of Chriſt who hath accompliſhed all.</p>
            <p>And the renewing of them derogateth much from Chriſts ſoveraigne ſacrifice, for it implieth imperfection in the ſame, As St. <hi>Paul</hi> proveth, by the legall ſacrifices offered ſo often becauſe they were imperfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen</hi> writeth thus in his Treatiſe on <hi>Matthew, veniente Principe Sacerdotum, the Prince of Prieſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, the Prieſt in figure ceaſed. The Temple made of ſtones is deſtroyed, to giue place to the Temple made of lively ſtones: Effoſſum eſt Altare quod erat deor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum: The Altar below on earth was broken downe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27942:11"/> becauſe the heavenly Altar had appeared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What haue we then to doe with them if they be paſt and gone? Surely nothing. True Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ever ſince their Lords death, haue left them both Prieſts and Altars to Iewes and Gentiles.</p>
            <p>But the whore of <hi>Babylons</hi> baſtardly brood, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon their Mothers beauty, that painted Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> haue laboured to reſtore her all her robes and iewells againe: eſpecially her looking glaſſe the Maſſe, in which ſhe may behold all her bravery.</p>
            <p>For they deſpiſing the plaine ſimplicity and modeſt attire of that graue matron Chriſts holy ſpouſe haue turned her officers all out of dores with all hir houſhold ſtuffe, hir Tables, hir Cupps, hir bookes, hir Communions, the very names of hir Miniſters, and ſuch like words vſed by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt throughout the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>In ſtead whereof the words Prieſt, and Altar, are taken vp by them; becauſe without Prieſt no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice can be offered; without Prieſt and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice there is no vſe of an Altar: and without all 3. Prieſts, Sacrifice, and Altar, there can be no Maſſe.</p>
            <p>But the Maſſe comming in brings in with it an inundation of Ceremonies, Croſſes, and Crucifix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and Challices, and Images, Copes, and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, and Tapers, and Baſons, and a thouſand ſuch Trinckets; which attend vpon the Maſſe: All which wee haue ſeene in this Church ſince the Communion table was turned to an Altar.</p>
            <p>Yet indeed it is no Altar, that's but a nick-name, it is wrongfully ſo called. For if it be an Altar there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27942:12"/> muſt needes be a Sacrifice offered by a Prieſt to God; but in the Communion nothing is offered to God but prayers, but praiſe and thanksgiving, which the hearts and lipps of all faithfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants offer to God by their Mediator Chriſt.</p>
            <p>They lay them not on a Table, they lay not their thanks, they lay not their prayers vpon an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, either of wood, or ſtone; as the Aaronicall Prieſts, laid their burnt offerings and incenſe.</p>
            <p>We ſet indeed the bread and wine vpon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, beſigning them to a Sacramentall vſe by the conſecration of Gods holy word: we doe not offer them to God, but God offereth them, and giveth them to vs, and with them his ſonne Chriſt, if we be faithfull and worthy receivers.</p>
            <p>To ſuch they are in deed and in truth ſpiritually, and Sacramentally, the very body and blood of Chriſt, then which more holy things the whole world affordeth not.</p>
            <p>But if it be an Altar as Maſſe-prieſts and out prieſts vſe to call it; and the body and blood of Chriſt a ſacrifice to God offered thereon, then is the Altar better, and more holy then the body of Chriſt, for it ſanctifieth it.</p>
            <p>Marke this, if the table whether wood or ſtone be an Altar, it is better then the body of Chriſt, and holier, (which to ſay or think is horrible blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) it is holier I ſay becauſe it ſanctifieth Chriſts body and blood if it be an Altar.</p>
            <p>For without contradiction ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 7. v. <hi>the leſſe is bleſſed of the better,</hi> proving there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that <hi>Melchiſedecke</hi> was a better man then <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:27942:12"/> and we know that to bleſſe is to conſecrate or ſanctifie.</p>
            <p>So ſaith our Saviour in the 23. of <hi>Matth. 3. v.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooving the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who taught, <hi>whoſoever ſhall ſweare by the Altar it is nothing, but whoſoever ſhall ſweare by the gift, that is the ſacrifice vpon the Altar, he is guilty, Ye fooles and blinde, whether is greater the gift or the Altar that ſanctifieth the gift.</hi> So ſay I to ſuch fond and ignorant teachers, who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues prieſts and the table an Altar.</p>
            <p>Ye blinde popiſh prieſts vnderſtand ye not that by erecting an Altar ye advance it aboue the body of Chriſt, ye make it better then Chriſts body, by making it a ſacrifice ſanctified by the Altar.</p>
            <p>And I am verily perſuaded that ſome there are, who eſteeme more of it then they doe of Chriſts body.</p>
            <p>For I haue ſeene, I haue ſeene I ſay the prieſt (ſo will he needs be called) take vp the body and blood after conſecration, and holding them in his hands, make a low legg to the Altar; and before he ſet them downe againe bow himſelfe devoutly and worſhip the Altar.</p>
            <p>He yeelded no reverence at all to Chriſts body, neither when he held it in his owne, nor when he had delivered it, into the receivers hands.</p>
            <p>What is it to preferre a ſtone or a peece of wood before the body of Chriſt if this be not? to bow to his altar, and not to his body, to make many leggs to the Kings chaire, and none to the King himſelf.</p>
            <p>And this is evident by their daily practiſe, for the altar is every day worſhipped with ducking to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27942:13"/> it, though there be no Communion, nor any man there; Chriſts body is not worſhipped with duck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no not at the Communion: Is it not worſe then popery?</p>
            <p>But the Fathers many times call it an <hi>Altar.</hi> It is true, for the myſtery of iniquity began betime to worke by ſmall beginnings lurking in words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacerdotes, Altaria, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Altars,</hi> and reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them which Gods Spirit had taught, and the Apoſtles ever vſed, <hi>Miniſtros &amp; Menſas, Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Tables,</hi> that way might be made for <hi>Antichrist</hi> and his abominable ſacrifice of the Maſſe.</p>
            <p>Yet the Fathers worſhipped not their altars: <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine, was the firſt that mentioneth geniculation,</hi> that is ducking to altars, which he learned of his Maſter <hi>Montanus,</hi> the firſt founder of croſſings, and duckings, and many other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall fooleries, to which he annexed the gift of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Tortullian,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chemnitius, was the authour, omnium fere Ceremoniarum Papiſticarum; in a manner of all Popiſh Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon aroſe an opinion that <hi>Montanus</hi> the heretick was the holy Ghoſt; that he claimed the name, vertue, and dignity of the holy Ghoſt; which is not credible ſo learned a Doctour as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> could belieue.</p>
            <p>But hee aſcribed as the papiſts doe, ſuch power and holineſſe to the Ceremonies which <hi>Montanus</hi> had deviſed, that without them none could bee partakers of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>As if the holy Ghoſt were annexed to Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27942:13"/> included in Ceremonies, collated by Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>Whereupon ſaith <hi>Bugenhagius</hi> a learned <hi>German, The Church of Rome condemned</hi> Montanus <hi>for an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, and yet nevertheleſſe retained his hereſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hereby is manifeſt, in that the books which defend his hereſies are preſerved, but the workes of thoſe Fathers which confuted them are loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montanus</hi> therefore was the firſt Altar worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and they that now imitate him in ducking to Altars are little better then hereticall <hi>Montaniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But giue me leaue I pray you to aske this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, why bow you not the knee to the font alſo, it being <hi>Lavacrum regenerationis, the laver of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> as honourable, and a more neceſſary Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
            <p>For without Baptiſme none can bee ſaved, as ſome teach; but many that are baptiſed dye, before they come to the yeares of diſcretion, and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may be fit to receiue the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, yet we ſee none make leggs to the Font.</p>
            <p>Why doe they not? Chriſt is as much preſent there, and as really, and the Font is an Altar as well as the Table, and ſo it was termed in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church by <hi>Prudentius,</hi> who lived 1300. yeares agoe.</p>
            <p>Who ſpeaking of a combate betweene Chaſtity and Luſt, after Chaſtity had killed Luſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abolens Baptiſmate labem, Catholico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Templ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> divini Fontis ad Aram Conſecrat gladium:</hi> (ſaith he)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having waſhed away her ſpotts in Baptiſme ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrates
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27942:14"/> her ſword, wherewith ſhe ſlew her enemie, to the Catholick Church, and hangs it vp, Fontis ad Aram, at the Altar of the Font.</hi> Loe here the Font alſo is called an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tar.</p>
            <p>Therefore honour ye the Font as well as the Table with one and the ſame worſhip of bowing the knee to it, or elſe you are hereticks, affording more holineſſe and more dignity to one Altar, and to one Sacrament, then to the other.</p>
            <p>For either your worſhip is religious, or civill; if it bee civill yee are abſurd ideots in honouring ſtocks and ſtones more then any poore man who is the image of God; for who will low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> too low to a begger as to ſweep the ground with his beard, if it be not very ſhort.</p>
            <p>If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be religious you are more abſurd in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the memory of Chriſts body and blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole Trinity: Seeing you are baptiſed in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, and not in the name of Chriſt alone.</p>
            <p>The Lords Table therefore and the Font they are Altars both alike, as an apple and an egg are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions both alike; that is neither of them properly and truly, though they haue a kind of reſemblance, and being both alike, and of equall worthineſſe, why are they ſo farr put aſunder the whole length of the Church, one at the head, the other at the foote?</p>
            <p>Why are they not ſet in the body of the Church or quire, being the fitteſt place to receiue the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt aſſemblies and moſt Communicants.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:27942:14"/>
            <p>Why is the Altar lifted vp to the top of the Sanctuary or Chancell, and the Font not admitted ſo much as to the bottome? It is not ſuffered to ſtand in the wonted place behinde the quire dore, why is one preferred as holier then the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sacraments of equall dignity.</p>
            <p>In St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church at <hi>Zuricke</hi> the Lords Table and the Font or Baptiſtory ſtood both in one place as witneſſeth <hi>Hoſpinian:</hi> and ſo they ſtood here all the time of our former Biſhops, till the proud Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar mounting aloft, ſhouldered the poore Font out of the quire, and toſſing it from poſt to pillar thruſt it almoſt quite out of dores.</p>
            <p>Doe I ſay almoſt? 'tis out of the Church quite, for one thing is <hi>Templum,</hi> another thing <hi>Eccleſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia</hi> is the <hi>Church</hi> where a congregation of people vſeth to aſſemble, to heare the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, which in Latine is <hi>Concio,</hi> and it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth not onely the Sermon, but <hi>caetum,</hi> the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude meeting together to heare Gods word.</p>
            <p>And the Preacher is called <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> or <hi>Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator,</hi> derived from the ſame words.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I conclude that where no congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation vſeth to meete to heare Sermons, that place is no Church; and conſequently the Font being ſet in no place of aſſembly, it is not in the Church: I confeſſe it is, <hi>in Templo,</hi> in part of this vaſt fabrike, but there it is where the people never meet to hear Gods word preached no more then they doe in the ſteeple where the bells hang.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe St. <hi>Bernard</hi> reprehended in his time, <hi>Templorum immenſas altitudines, et immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratas
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27942:15"/> longitudines; the exceſsiue heights, and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate lengths of Temples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why ſo? becauſe he miſliked worldly magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in the ſpirituall ſervice of God, who dwells not in Temples made with hands.</p>
            <p>Alſo, becauſe he would not haue the Miniſter and people ſundred, nor ſcattered abroad in ſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous roomes, but ioyned together as neere as might be. Who ſtanding in the midſt, <hi>vugli ſtante co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona,</hi> the people all about him, round in a ring, he may better be heard, and they edified.</p>
            <p>For all things in the Church, ought to be done to edification, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> which then is beſt, when the Miniſter abides with the people, or they draw neere to him: He may not runne away in a <hi>Cope,</hi> as farre as he can get him from the congregation.</p>
            <p>But what a tricke is this which our newfangled Ceremony-mongers have taken vp of late, to goe in a <hi>Cope</hi> to the Altar, to ſay two or three prayers after the Sermon? why vſe they this ceremony, not mentioned in the Communion booke or Canons?</p>
            <p>Why ſuffer they not the Preacher to diſmiſſe the congregation with the bleſſing of Gods peace as was wont to be done, and our laſt Biſhop eſteemed to be beſt.</p>
            <p>How dare they put off, and put on a <hi>Cope</hi> ſo often in one ſervice, not onely to pray, but to reade the Epiſtle and Goſpell, and ten commandements at the Altar onely, and no other place where the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany and other ſervice is read, there being no ſuch thing appointed in the Booke of Common praier? And the Canons according to the advertiſements
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27942:15"/> publiſhed in the ſeventh yeare of Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> commanding no <hi>Copes</hi> to be vſed, but Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, when all other prayers are ſaid at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion table; ſaue onely at the adminiſtration of the holy Communion.</p>
            <p>Why doe they theſe things contrary to law? and never done in our Church before ſince the Maſſe was baniſhed?</p>
            <p>Is it becauſe they are enamoured with <hi>Copes?</hi> doe they dote vpon <hi>Copes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or are the Pſalmes and Chapters read in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church not ſo good Goſpel, nor ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be coped?</p>
            <p>Or is there ſo neere affinity betweene <hi>Copes</hi> and <hi>Altars,</hi> are they ſo married together that they can not be parted?</p>
            <p>Or thinke they their prayers and other ſervice more holy in ſuch prieſtly veſtiments, <hi>in ſancto ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> in that moſt holy place ſo devoutly duckt vnto, by our fooliſh, bewitched, and beſotted <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, why ſing they the <hi>Nicen Creed</hi> in a <hi>Cope</hi> at the Altar, the booke appointing it to be ſaid as the Apoſtles Creed is ſaid, not ſung.</p>
            <p>Why make they the people to ſtand vp when it is ſung, that ceremony of ſtanding being forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by law, by which you that ſtand, (marke what I ſay) you that ſtand are to be puniſhed for obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch vnlawfull commands, as I mean to proue when time ſhall ſerue?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, why forbid they ſinging of Pſalmes in ſuch a tune, as all the people may ſing with them,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27942:16"/> and praiſe God together, before and after Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as by authority is allowed, and heretofore hath beene practiſed both here and in all refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches?</p>
            <p>How dare they in ſtead of Pſalmes, appoint An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thems, (little better then prophane Ballads ſome of them I ſay, ſo many Anthems to be ſung, which none of the people vnderſtand, nor all the ſingers themſelues, which the preface to the Communion booke, and the Queenes Iniunctions, will haue cut off, becauſe the people is not edified by them?</p>
            <p>It is for ſpite they beare to <hi>Geneva,</hi> which all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hate, or for the loue of <hi>Rome,</hi> which becauſe they cannot imitate in having Latine ſervice, yet they will come as neer it as they can, in having ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in Engliſh ſo ſaid and ſung, that few or none can vnderſtand the ſame? I blame not the ſingers, moſt of which miſlike theſe prophane innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though they be forced to follow them?</p>
            <p>Their guides are in fault, blinde guides, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our Church, rotten members I doubt, of higher degree; to whom all men and women are rank puritans and ſchiſmaticks, to be thruſt outand expeld, if they refuſe to dance after their fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call pipe in every idle ceremony.</p>
            <p>Theſe cry with the <hi>Iewes, Templum Domini, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum Domini: The Church of God, the ſervice of God;</hi> when indeed their whole ſervice is little elſe then ſuperſtitious vanity.</p>
            <p>What is it but hypocriticall and Phariſaicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion? vnder the colour of long prayer, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and evening, and midday, they devoure,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27942:16"/> what devoure they? not poore widowes houſes, but rich benefices, whole townes and villages.</p>
            <p>For ſeldome ſhall you ſee a ſtout ceremony-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but the ſame will alſo be a notorious Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, a very Tot-Quot; not content with one or two little ones, but foure or fiue great preferments and dignities.</p>
            <p>And ſtill he aſpireth, and climeth higher, never thinking himſelfe ſufficiently rewarded for his great learning, and ſervice of God, in ſitting at Church three times a day, to heare men pipe, and chaunt, and chaunt himſelfe where he liſteth.</p>
            <p>A baſe imployment, prohibited by Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> himſelfe; who ſpeaking <hi>de cantu Eccleſiaſtico,</hi> hath theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prohibitum eſt ne quit in Eccleſia cantet, niſi inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores ordines, vtpote Subdiaconi; Diaconi vero lectioni &amp; praedicationi incumbant. It is forbidden,</hi> ſaith the Pope, <hi>that any chaunt in Churches, but men of meane degree, none aboue Subdeacons; but Miniſters or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, muſt apply themſelues to reading and preaching;</hi> for that makes moſt for the peoples edification, to which all muſt be done.</p>
            <p>And when we take orders of the Biſhop, charge is given to reade, and preach Gods word, not to ſing: any lewd Lay-man can doe that, without laying on of a Biſhops hands, without conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I was not ſent to baptiſe,</hi> (much leſſe to ſing in a quire) <hi>but to preach.</hi> And, <hi>woe to me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if I preach not the Goſpell:</hi> he ſaith not, woe to me, if I obſerue not the canonicall houres of devotion in ſinging.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:27942:17"/>
            <p>This makes me call to remembrance, a ſtrange ſpeech little better then blaſphemy, vttered lately by a young man, in the preſence of his Lord, and many learned men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I had rather goe forty miles to a good ſervice, then two miles to a Sermon.</hi> (Os durum.)</p>
            <p>And what meant he by a good ſervice? his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was manifeſt; where goodly Babyloniſh robes were worne, imbroydered with images.</p>
            <p>Where he might heare a delicate noiſe of ſingers, with Shakebuts, and Cornets, and Organs, and if it were poſſible, all kinde of Muſicke, vſed at the dedication of <hi>Nabuchodonoſors</hi> golden Image.</p>
            <p>To ſuch a dainty ſervice of heavenly Harmony, the ſingular devotion, and hot zeale of this holy man, would carry him over hills and dales, through fire and water, rather forty miles, then two miles to a Sermon.</p>
            <p>How think you? was not this a profane, witleſſe, graceleſſe, Antichriſtian ſaying, which preferreth piping, and ſinging before Gods ordinance of preaching.</p>
            <p>Yet learned <hi>Aretius,</hi> that famous <hi>Helvetian</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, ſticks not to ſay: <hi>In Papatu, cantus Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus omnia peſſundat, adeo vt pro doctrina, perpetua regnat Muſica. In the Popes Kingdome Church chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting marrs all, inſomuch as in stead of the perpetuall ſounding of Gods holy word, in the hearts of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the ſound of muſicall melody, rings in their eares,</hi> and raignes in their mindes, they are ſo tickled, nay raviſhed with the delight thereof.</p>
            <p>But what ſay by him who accuſing our fathers,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27942:17"/> not long ſince ſaid: when they baniſhed Popery by taking away the Maſſe, that they tooke away all religion, and the whole ſervice of God? they called it a reformation, ſaith he, but it was indeed a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, whereby Gods ſervice was diſordered and mard.</p>
            <p>But now the caſe is altered, for of late yeares, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath beene begun, prettily well to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe in this Church: and by the boldneſſe of reſolute and couragious officers, way is made for reducing of the Maſſe.</p>
            <p>For before we had Miniſters, as the Scripture calls them, we had Communion tables, we had Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments: but now we haue Prieſts, and Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Altars, with much Altar furniture, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Maſſing implements. Nay what want we? haue not all religion againe?</p>
            <p>For if religion conſiſt in Altar-ducking, Cope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearing, Organ-playing, piping and ſinging.</p>
            <p>Croſſing of chuſhions, and kiſſing of clouts, oft ſtarting vp, and ſquatting downe, nodding of heads, and whirling about, till their noſes ſtand Eaſtward.</p>
            <p>Setting Baſons on the Altar, Candleſticks and Crucifixes; burning Waxe-candles, in exceſſiue number, when and where there is no vſe of Lights.</p>
            <p>And that which is worſt of all, guilding of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and garniſhing of Images, and ſetting them vp aloft; whereas <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith, <hi>procul dubio i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi nulla eſt religio vbi ſunt Simulacra: without doubt there is no religion in that Church, where Images are placed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:27942:18"/>
            <p>If I ſay religion conſiſt in theſe and ſuch like ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious vanities, ceremoniall fooleries, apiſh toyes, and popiſh trinckets, we had never more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then now.</p>
            <p>And though our Leiturgy be not in Latine, yet order is taken, by confuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dneſſe of voices, ſome ſqueaking, ſome blating, ſome roaring, and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering with a multitude of melodious inſtruments that the greateſt part of the ſervice, is no better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, then if it were in Hebrew or Iriſh.</p>
            <p>Nay the Sacrament it ſelfe is turned well neare into a theatricall ſtage play, that when mens minds ſhould be occupied about heavenly meditations, of Chriſts bitter death and paſſion, of their owne ſinnes, of faith and repentance, of the ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the torments of hell: At that very ſeaſon, very vnſeaſonably, their eares are poſſeſt with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant tunes, and their eyes fed with pompous ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles, of gliſtering pictures, and hiſtrionicall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, repreſenting vnto vs <hi>Apollo's</hi> ſolemnities in his Temple at <hi>Delos,</hi> which the Poet deſcribeth in his fourth of his Aeneiods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſtaurat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> charos, miſti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Altaria circum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Creteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Dryopeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fremunt picti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Agathyrſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our young <hi>Apollo</hi> repaireth the quire, and ſets it out gayly, with ſtrange Babyloniſh ornaments; the hallowed Prieſts daunce about the Altar, making pretty ſport, and fyne paſtime, with trippings, and turnings, and croſſings, and crouchings; while <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Dryopeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> picti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Agathyrſi,</hi> Choriſters, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-men, and parti-coloured Cope-wearers, <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt,</hi> they ſhout and cry, and make moſt ſweet <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollinian</hi> harmony.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:27942:18"/>
            <p>Are theſe ceremonies fit for the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? <hi>Doe this,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>in remembrance of mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can theſe paltry toyes bring to our memory Chriſt and his blood-ſhedding?</p>
            <p>Did Chriſt miniſter the Sacrament in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to his Diſciples at his laſt Supper?</p>
            <p>Was there an Altar in the chamber where he ſupt? Did Chriſt put on a Cope laden with Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Or did he change his garments? ſaith <hi>Hamin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Apage ineptias,</hi> fie vpon fopperies, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious vanities, I hate them.</p>
            <p>A decent Cope is commanded by our Canons to be vſed ſometimes, onely at the Communion.</p>
            <p>Whether a ſtately Cope, a ſumptuous Cope, a Cope imbroydered with Idols, of ſilver, gold, and pearle: a mock-Cope, a ſcornfull Cope, vſed a long time at Maſſe and May-games, as ſome of ours were: Whether I ſay ſuch a Cope, be a decent Cope, fit for the Lords table, iudge ye beloved.</p>
            <p>And if you condemn them, as you cannot chuſe if you be good Chriſtians; how dare ye communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with vs in our ſuperſtitious vanities?</p>
            <p>Haue you not Churches at home in your owne Pariſhes not yet polluted with Idols; and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion tables not yet changed into Altars?</p>
            <p>Where you may receiue with comfort the holy Communion, (without ſuch All-a-flantara) in plaine and ſimple manner, as our Saviour ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the primitiue Church practiſed, till An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt aroſe, and mightily prevailed againſt the truth.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:27942:19"/>
            <p>Stay at home in the name of God, till things be amended, and reduced to the ſtate and forme they were in our leſſe ceremonious, and more preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Biſhops time.</p>
            <p>Duck no more to our Altar when you come in and goe out: I aſſure it is an Idol, a damnable Idol as it is vſed.</p>
            <p>Remember Gods commandement <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe, the likeneſſe of any thing in heaven aboue, or in the earth beneath, thou ſhall not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them:</hi> How dare you diſobey God, nay mock God, as the Prieſt doth, who ſtands at the Altar in a Cope, and there reades with a loud voice, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them;</hi> and as ſoone as he hath done reading, as when he began to reade, he turnes him about, bowes downe againe, and worſhips the Altar.</p>
            <p>Is not this deriſion of God and mockery? <hi>Be not deceived,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Theos ou muctereſetai, God is not, God will not be mocked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beleeue not thoſe <hi>Balaams,</hi> which lay ſtumbling blocks in your way, to make you fall into ſpirituall fornication, telling you, when you bow to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, you worſhip God, not the Altar, for ſo anſwer all popiſh and heatheniſh Idolaters.</p>
            <p>Tell me this? Is not that woman a whore, who yeelds her body to an adulterer? though ſhe ſay her minde is chaſte, ſhe keeps her heart true to her husband.</p>
            <p>So ſay I, They are whores, and whoremongers, they commit ſpirituall fornication, who bow their bodies, before that Idol the Altar, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27942:19"/> they ſay, their mindes are cleane, they lift vp their hearts to heaven.</p>
            <p>God appointed Altars to be ſet vp by King <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> in his Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> They were true Altars, types and figures of Chriſt to come, as the Prieſts and Sacrifices were: yet Gods people bowed not to them, nor worſhipped them.</p>
            <p>No nor the Arke of the Covenant, a ſymbolicall ſigne of Gods perpetuall preſence; which was ſo ſacred, that none but conſecrated hands might touch it, no nor the cart that carried it; they might not look into it, as the men of <hi>Bethſhemis</hi> did, of whom 50 thouſand died preſently for that treſpaſſ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> indeed danced before it, on the way as it came from the houſe of <hi>Obed Edom,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence he turned his back toward it, (vnleſſe he leapt backward all the way in his dance;) we reade not that he bowed his body to it, or duckt ſo low, as to touch the ground with his noſe.</p>
            <p>How dare ye then bow downe and worſhip an Altar, a counterfeit Altar, the Image of an Altar, and no better.</p>
            <p>Why feare you to turne your backs to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar? Are the backs of Chriſtian men and women more prophane then the backs of <hi>Iewes,</hi> that by no meanes they may ſit, or ſtand, or kneele, with their backs eaſtward?</p>
            <p>But they muſt turne about, and looke on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar when they pray, or heare the Goſpell, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe the articles of their faith.</p>
            <p>Ye fooliſh <hi>Galathians,</hi> what <hi>Iannes,</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> Aegyptian Sorcerers haue bewitched you, that you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27942:20"/> ſhould follow ſo readily ſuch vaine ſuperſtitions, and beggerly rudiments.</p>
            <p>Ye may not be hold altars, aſcribing holineſſe to them: you muſt looke vp to God, and his Sonne Chriſt when you pray.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> had onely two altars; they were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Chriſt to come: thoſe ſhadowes are paſt and gone: the altars are demoliſhed: you may not make new to gaze vpon ſuperſtitiouſly, but you muſt looke to your maker.</p>
            <p>As God himſelfe expreſly commandeth in the 17. ch. of the Prophecy of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 7. v. Reade it. <hi>At that day ſhall a man looke to his Maker, and his eyes ſhall haue reſpect to the holy one of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he ſhall not looke to the altars, the workes of his hands, neither ſhall he reſpect that which his fingers haue made, either groues or Images, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, or Candleſticks.</p>
            <p>Why will ye be <hi>Throma koi,</hi> fighters againſt God in reſiſting his will, and doing the thing he ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly forbids.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God will wound the hairy ſcalpe,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, of him that continueth in his wickedneſſe.</hi> Take heed of Gods vengeance, if you continue in your folly, which I pray God giue you grace to leaue.</p>
            <p>Hearken what <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith, that excellent Divine, diſputing againſt <hi>Wincheſter, Si vel Angelus de coelo nos provocare velit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> adoranda vel Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, vel Altaria, vel honorem divinum rebus creatis exhibendum, Anathema ſit. If an Angel from heaven would provoke vs to adore either Sacrament or Altar, or any other creature, let him be accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:27942:20"/>
            <p>And it is moſt certaine that every creature that is bowed vnto in reſpect of any holineſſe therein for religion ſake, that religious worſhip makes it an Idol: of which ſort the Altar is one, a notable one, religiouſly adored in this Church every day.</p>
            <p>Therefore learned <hi>Chemnitius,</hi> in treating of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and reckoning vp all manner of Idols, he names <hi>Altaria,</hi> expreſly <hi>Altars,</hi> among the ſame.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>I doe not think,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr, that any of the Fathers were polluted with ſo groſſe Idolatry, as to bow their bodies before Altars, eſpecially when there is no Communion,</hi> as is daily done at <hi>Durham,</hi> not to the place, but to the very ſtone, when they ſtand cloſe by the Altar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if at any time,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they ſhall be diſcovered to haue beene ſuch, (Altar-worſhippers) let none of vs be led by their books, or examples, vt à iusta obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia divinae legis aberret, to decline from the ſtrict obſervation of Gods law, which peremptorily forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the making of Idols, and bowing to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Lords table is no Idol, no nor Altar, if it be the Lords boord, as the Communion booke rightly names it.</p>
            <p>For which <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> ſcoffingly accuſeth vs, <hi>that we haue no Altars, but Tables, or Boords, ad comedendum &amp; bibendum, to eate and drink at.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> anſwereth very well: <hi>Quid opus eſt Altari, vbi nec ignis ardeat, nec victimae caedantur? what vſe is there of an Altar, where no fire burnes, nor beaſts are ſlaine for ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shew me either out of the words of Chriſt, or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27942:21"/> the Apoſtles doctrine, any commandement for the erecting of Altars.</p>
            <p>We haue tables, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtles calls them, who knew well enough, that Chriſt did inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the myſtery of the Euchariſt, at his laſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, not at an altar, but a table.</p>
            <p>There he ſupt, there he brake bread; and we know, men vſe to ſup, and breake bread, not vpon altars, but at tables.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Arnobius</hi> teſtifie, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their time, 1400. yeeres ſince, made the ſame ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection againſt Chriſtians, that they had not altars.</p>
            <p>If therefore there were none in the primitiue Church, which was moſt pure; why ſhould we borrow them now of the corrupt Popiſh Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what ſay you?</hi> ſaith one of our Ceremonie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, <hi>are not Altars mentioned in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we haue an Altar, whereof they haue no right to eate which ſerue the Tabernacle, Hebr. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in the 6. of the Revel. 9. v. I ſaw vnder the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, the ſoules of them that were ſlaine for the word of God. Loe here Altars are plainly named. Is not this a ſubſtantiall proofe, that our Church now hath Altars?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O learned head! Thinks he indeed that all the Martyrs ſoules, which ſince Chriſts time haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for the teſtimony of Ieſus, are lodged ſo coldly vnder an altar ſtone; wailing and crying, ſome of them ſixteene hundred yeeres, <hi>How long Lord, how long wilt thou avenge our blood?</hi> and yet poore ſoules there muſt abide till doomes day. A damnable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
            <p>I would faine learne of ſuch a dreaming Divine,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27942:21"/> there being ſo many Altars in the Chriſtian world, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which of them lie ſo many millions of ſoules: for St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes but of one Altar, <hi>I ſaw vnder the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi> I pray you is not this Altar Chriſt, <hi>the Altar of the faithfull,</hi> Eſa. 56.</p>
            <p>So it is expounded by all learned Divines, both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Proteſtants. And among the reſt, by one, whoſe authority the proudeſt Altar-worſhipper dare not gain ſay: I meane the King, <hi>Theologus Rex,</hi> that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Prince King <hi>Iames,</hi> who in his paraphraſe on the <hi>Revelation,</hi> hath theſe words, interpreting that text. <hi>I ſaw vnder the Altar the ſoules of the Martyrs, which cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a loud voice, How long wilt thou delay ô Lord, ſince thou art holy and true, to revenge our blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For perſecution it makes ſo great a number of Martyrs, that the ſoules lying vnder the Altar, to wit in the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Ieſus Chriſt, (who is the onely Altar, whereupon, and by whom it is onely lawfull for vs to offer the ſacrifice of hearts and lipps, to wit, our humble prayers to God the Father.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They did pray, and their blood did cry to heaven, and craue at the hands of their Father a iuſt revenge of their torments vpon the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then white robes were given to every one of them: Which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ought to be a wonderfull comfort to all the Church militant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since by this they be aſſured, that the ſoules of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, ſo ſoone as their bodies are killed ſhall immediately be rewarded, with bright glory in heaven, not going into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other place by the way, which is ſignified by the white robes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus for his Maieſties royall pen: by whom we are taught, that Chriſt is our one and onely Altar, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27942:22"/> that the ſoules of the Saints, being preſently rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with glory in heaven, and not going to any other place by the way, none of them are vnder our Altar, (though it be a braue one) for it is out of their way to heaven from the place where they ſuffered Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>As for that place, <hi>Hebr. 13. We haue an Altar, &amp;c.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe expounds it afterwards, in the 15 verſe, to be Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>by him therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et vs offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to God continually, that is, the fruit of our lips, giving thanks to his name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas, cannot be vnderſtood of a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Altar in the Church:</hi> and whoſoever thinks it to be ſo, he is therein more popiſh, then Frier <hi>Thomas</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But now I come to their maine argument, which they think quite overthrowes all that I haue ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Altars, and Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kings Chappell,</hi> ſay they, <hi>hath an Altar, and all furniture belonging thereunto: Dare you diſallow in ours, what the King hath in his? It is little better then trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> as one ſaid.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, It was never out of the Kings Chappell, (at leaſt the name of an altar) ſince the firſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, if it had, I ſuppoſe it had never come in againe, in his religoius ſucceſſours raigne.</p>
            <p>But it hath been by law eiected out of this Church, and changed into a ſacred table, <hi>Ieran Bape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an,</hi> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls it, I marvell therefore, what law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe man, could reſtore it without law.</p>
            <p>Againe, what haue we doe with imitation of the Court<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> May we be ſo ſawcy, as to imitate the King in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27942:22"/> all things? Is it not treaſon? Is not rebellion ſo to doe?</p>
            <p>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old preſumption is this in a Prieſt or Prelate to take vpon him to be like the King without his leaue, and not to ſuffer for his Maieſty to haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary, aboue the vulgar ſort in magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence and ſtate.</p>
            <p>The King commands vs to obey his lawes, not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate his Chappell contrary to his lawes, which binde Cathedrall Churches as well as as the reſt; none are exempted, none can be diſpenſt withall.</p>
            <p>The law is this. <hi>The Communion Table, not Altar, ſhall ſtand in the body of the Church, or Chancell, where morning and evening prayer be appointed to be ſaid, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhall ſtand at the northſide of the Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore our Communion table muſt ſtand as it had wont to doe, in the midſt of the quire: not at the eaſt end, as farre as is poſſible from the people, where no part at all of evening prayer is ever ſaid, and but a peece of the morning, and that never till of late.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt the Table be placed along from north to ſouth, as the altar is ſet, but from eaſt to weſt, as the cuſtome is of all reformed Churches: otherwiſe, the Miniſter cannot ſtand at the north ſide, there being neither ſide toward the north.</p>
            <p>And I trow there are but two ſides of a long table, and two ends: make it ſquare, and then it will haue foure ſides, and no end, or foure ends, and no ſide, at which any Miniſter can ſtand to celebrate.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, it is not materiall, which way a man turne his face, when he miniſters, and prayeth, if it be left as a thing indifferent, without ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cum quis quaerit orare, collocat membra ſic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ei occurrit: when any mangoes about to pray, be pleaſeth his body as occaſion ſerveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:27942:23"/>
            <p>And St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth every man to lift vp pure hands, whether toward the eaſt, or weſt, it makes no matter.</p>
            <p>Yet indeed, it is more dangerous to pray toward the eaſt, becauſe the idolatrous Heathen which worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Sun riſing, did ſo.</p>
            <p>And it was the cuſtome of the Iewes, to pray weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, leſt they ſhould be entiſed, to worſhip the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entall Sunne, as the Heathen did.</p>
            <p>Which God himſelfe in the 8. chap. of Ezech. 16. v. reckoneth among the abominations of the idolatrous Iſraelites, who turning their backs toward the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, worſhipped the Sunne toward the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Iewes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine, which ſerved the Lord, prayed toward the Weſt:</hi> Therefore Chriſtians muſt turne them toward the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>A bolde reaſon: The Iewes did well in avoiding all occaſion of Idolatry, vnto which the vulgar ſort is too prone: as appeareth by the people of this place, how ſoone learned they to bow downe to the Altar, and worſhip it. The Iewes I ſay did well, therefore may Chriſtians doe ill, in imitating the idolatrous Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, in that fooliſh, popiſh, ſuperſtitious obſervation, of turning their faces eaſtward when they pray.</p>
            <p>And why may we not imitate the Iewes, in the things they did well, the reaſon of their ſo doing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ceremoniall, but morall?</p>
            <p>The ceremoniall law is indeed abrogated therefore we may not retaine it; but the morall law is ſtill in force, binding both Iewes and Chriſtians to avoid I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry.</p>
            <p>But ſee the ſhameleſneſſe of a doting Ieſuite: he is content we ſhould imitate the Iewes in their ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27942:23"/> long ſince diſanulled and ended, in having Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Sacrifices, Prieſts, prieſtly veſtiments, oyntments, incenſe: But he will not haue vs be like the Iewes, in caſting Idols out of our Churches, and in ſhunning all occaſions of Idolatry, by turning our backs on the Eaſt, when we pray, as they did.</p>
            <p>Our good Princes, and learned Biſhops, when they began to reforme the Church of England, were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that wee ſhould bee like the Iewes rather in this point, then the idolatrous Papiſts, or Gentiles.</p>
            <p>And therefore they ordeined by law, that the Communion table ſhould not ſtand Altarwiſe, the two ends looking to the ſouth and north, as of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Altars were ſet in Popery, that the Maſſe prieſt might ſtand on the weſt ſide, with his face toward the Eaſt, and his back to the people.</p>
            <p>But contrariwiſe, they appointed the table to bee placed in the midſt of the Church, to be moveable, faſtned neither to wall, nor floore, the ends ſtanding from Eaſt to Weſt, as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p>And they preciſely inioyned the Miniſter to ſtand at the celebration of the Lords Supper, on the north ſide of the Table, to the intent they ſhould not be like ſuperſtitious ſhauelings.</p>
            <p>Which make mee to wonder at the preſumptuous boldneſſe of him, or them, which immediately after the death of our laſt learned Biſhop, before wee had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, about eleven yeares ago, took vpon him, (I know not by what authority) to alter the ſituation of the Communion table, from the ould manner of ſtanding which it had kept in all Biſhops times, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raigne, ſaue onely when the Rebels poſſeſt this Church, and ſang Maſſe therin.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:27942:24"/>
            <p>The Lords table I ſay eleven yeares agoe was turned to an altar, and ſo placed, that the Miniſter cannot ſtand to doe his office on the north ſide, as the law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly chargeth him to doe, becauſe there is no ſide of the table ſtanding northward.</p>
            <p>He I ſay, that contrary to law d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt doe this, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Papiſts and Rebels, deſerues hee not to bee ſharply cenſured? why doe I ſay durſt he doe it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non audet ſtygius Pluto tentare quod audet Effrenis Monachus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Divellin hell dare not attempt more then an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Monke, or Frierdare doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Divell and a Frier will adventure ſtrangely: I haue heard of a Divell that preacht, I haue heard of a Frier that preacht in a rope; but I neuer heard of, either Divell or Frier, that preached in a Cope.</p>
            <p>But why is the Communion table ſet in the eaſt end of the Church, and not in the weſt end, or middle ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereas <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaith, in his 5 book, 21 chap. that in a Temple at <hi>Antioch,</hi> the altar was placed at the weſt end.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Gentean Hervet,</hi> a popiſh writer, deſcribing the faſhion of the Greeke Church at this time, ſaith, <hi>In Graeconum Templis, vnicum eſt Altare, ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in medio Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro: The Graecians haue but one Altar, in a Church, and that, in the middle of the Quire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore neither the <hi>Graecians,</hi> nor the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> looked eaſtward, but rather weſtward when they prayed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Binius</hi> alſo and <hi>Bawnius</hi> ſay, <hi>that becauſe the Manichees which dia worſhip the Sunne prayed toward the Eaſt.</hi> Leo <hi>the firſt ordeined, that to diſcerne Catholikes from here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> converſi Deum colerent: The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks ſhould worſhip toward the West.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:27942:24"/>
            <p>Afterward by the conſtitution of Pope <hi>Vigilius,</hi> it was ordeined, <hi>that the Miniſter ſtanding at the Altar, ſhould pray toward the Weſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It came therefore from Antichriſt to reſtrain Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, by commanding will-worſhip, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of men, without any warrant out of Gods word.</p>
            <p>Againe Necromancers and Sorcerers turne their faces to the Eaſt, when they act their inchantments: and it little becomes Chriſtians to follow Witches, and Coniurers, in their ſuperſtitious, and diveliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, by preferring Eaſt before Weſt.</p>
            <p>It being a Ceremony, of all other moſt fooliſh, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, Papiſticall, Paganicall, and Magicall.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore in the name of God, hate with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> the abominations, and ſuperſtitious vanities.</p>
            <p>If we hate them not, God will hate vs, and abhorre our feſtivities with all the pomp and glory of our Church.</p>
            <p>As he tolde the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the fifth of <hi>Amps, v. 21. I hate and abborre your feaſt dayes, I will not ſmell your ſolemne aſſemblies. Take away from me the noiſe of thy ſongs, I will not heare the melody of thy inſtruments: for ye haue borne the Tabernacle of</hi> Molocke, <hi>and</hi> Chiun <hi>your Images, the ſtarre of your God which you made to your ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such <hi>Molocks,</hi> ſuch <hi>Chiuns,</hi> ſuch Images and ſtarres ſome of vs here haue made to themſelues, lift vp your eyes, you praiſed them; ſet vp aloft, round this Church.</p>
            <p>Harke then what Chriſt ſaith to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, Revel.</hi> 2.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
